Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
What happened to your face?
It was my own blunder.
Petunia, stop watering the plants.
Go collect the stipend for this month.
Yes.
Petunia.
Where are you going?
Madam, Jade instructed me
to collect the stipend from the Household Department.
Oh? That's where I'm headed too.
Let's go together.
The Ministry of Rites has selected
three honorary names for the princess.
Which one do you like?
The Ministry of Rites always selects excellent names.
They are equally good.
The princess has a calm quiet temperament.
But I'm afraid Hongyan might be a naughty child.
In fact, I believe it's good for a prince to be rambunctious and outgoing.
Unlike Hongshi, who is always so cheerless, like an old man.
He acts like a mouse before a cat when he sees me.
Your Majesty chooses to be an exacting father.
You can't blame the child for being intimidated.
I promise you I will be only a kind father
in front of our children.
You should give serious thought to
selecting the honorary name for our princess.
"Although we have not the wings of a colorful phoenix,
our hearts are connected by the divine rhino's horn."
For the princess's honorary name,
how about the rhino's horn: "Lingxi"?
Lingxi.
For the past ten years, our hearts
have been connected as one.
So, our daughter is Princess Lingxi.
Your Majesty, My Lady,
it's time for the prince and princess to be nursed.
The wet nurse will escort them out.
Very well.
Yes.
That girl has been with you for several years.
She bears a resemblance to you
now that she has grown older.
Your Majesty has said this before.
You said Jade has similar eyes to mine.
Jade was only of middling beauty before.
Although her eyes were like yours,
she was just a girl who adorned herself
"all over with red and green."
Now that she has gotten older,
her temperament has grown more like yours.
What has gotten into Your Majesty today?
You keep on praising a maid like this.
It will provoke the laughter of others.
You are a mother now, but you become even more like a child.
If Jade were not your favored maid,
I might not even bother to give this compliment.
It was only that her growth reminded me of Longyue.
Longyue is growing up by the day.
She looks quite like you now.
When Longyue gets older,
I will allow her to return here
so that mother and daughter are no longer separated.
Longyue, do you like this little bunny?
Mother, I'd like a little tiger.
Oh dear, it's too difficult to cut out a little tiger.
I don't know how to make one.
Mother, you can make anything.
You know everything.
Of course, I can do anything for my Longyue.
I will learn how to make a little tiger.
Peace to Your Highness.
You may rise.
I thank Your Highness.
Her Noble Highness says
she hasn't had a chance to see you recently.
Since the weather is very nice today,
she invites Your Highness to join her
at the Palace of Eternal Longevity.
Very well, you may return first.
I will be there shortly.
Yes.
Your Highness, will you take the princess with you?
Longyue, stay here and wait for me.
I'll be back soon.
Lull the princess to sleep. I'll return soon.
Yes.
Consort Estime has arrived.
Your Noble Highness.
Estime, have a seat.
I finally have some time to myself today.
We sisters finally have some time to catch up.
Your Noble Highness just gave birth
to "a dragon and a phoenix"
and have to deal with the
burdensome etiquette and palace affairs.
I dare not come and disturb you.
Estime, you are calling me "Noble Highness" now.
It seems we might have become estranged.
You are being courteous, Lumière,
but there is a difference between inferior and superior.
You are the second Noble Consort
after Noble Consort Fleur.
This title is truly well deserved.
In regards to merit and experience,
are you not also deserving of this title?
Even so, not all Noble Consorts are the same.
I remember that after you left the palace,
His Majesty once mentioned
how he first met you in the Imperial Garden.
He could not cease praising your beautiful smile,
and said nothing in this world could describe it.
His Majesty had never forgotten you all those years.
"One glance at a youthful lady can bring an entire city to its knees."
But that beauty "withers in the snap of a finger."
One can do nothing but watch His Majesty's favor
flow away like a running river - the water of no return.
In the harem, some women's lives flourish,
while others' wither,
but ultimately, all of us live the same life.
It's fortunate that His Majesty has you in his heart.
You've always been wise, Estime, and able
to see everything as clearly as a bright flame.
Since you know that His Majesty treats me generously,
then why do you choose to go against me?
You've found out about it.
It was you who told the Empress
about Jinxi and Su Peisheng.
They are both discreet,
and the only evidence was that sachet
embroidered with willow leaves.
You recognized that it was Jinxi's work.
Only you and Meizhuang were present, aside from me.
Also, at that time you frequently visited
the Palace of Great Benevolence.
Your Noble Highness has a brilliant mind.
Why would you ask me
when you already know this?
It's good that you know now.
It will save me from a troubled conscience
when I eat and sleep.
I was the one who harmed you this time.
I owe you an apology.
You never compete for His Majesty's favor,
and seldom run afoul of anyone.
Even when Consort Fleur was in power,
you were able to endure her and protect yourself.
You only did this to keep Longyue by your side.
If not for Longyue,
I would have no moment of joy for the rest of my life.
Lumière, you've been deeply in His Majesty's favor
ever since you first served him.
How would you know the loneliness I feel in my desolate palace?
You know what?
There are three hundred and twenty-six masonry stones in my palace.
I've touched each and every one of them thousands of times.
And I know that fine cracks have appeared
on thirty-one of them.
How else could I get through the endless nights?
In fact, I knew from the beginning
that I was only His Majesty's pawn
to check Consort Fleur's influence.
You've never told me such things before, Estime.
When you entrusted me with Longyue,
I wished to depend on her for the rest of my life,
and to have some company to pass the lonesome nights.
All these years,
I've always considered Longyue to be my own flesh and blood.
I never imagined that you would return...
that you could ever come back!
Estime, did you know that
I did not learn of your visits to the
Palace of Great Benevolence through my own inquiries.
This information was deliberately revealed by the Empress.
If she truly wished to support you,
this information would have stayed secret.
Yet, for seemingly no reason at all,
it was passed on to me.
You don't need to think hard to understand why.
The Empress let you know intentionally.
She wants us to eliminate each other.
Lumière, please believe me.
It's not that I wanted to hurt you.
I just wanted Longyue to
stay by my side for a few more years.
Just a few more years.
I told the Empress,
I would do this just once. Only once.
But even so,
I still fell into her masterful hands.
Whether it is me bringing you down, or vice versa,
the Empress benefits either way.
It might not have been your lack of foresight -
you felt you had to take the risk because of Longyue.
A mother's love can truly blind one's eyes and cloud one's mind.
It was either you, or the Empress.
I had no other choice.
At this point, I have nothing more to say.
I am at the mercy of Your Noble Highness.
Then Estime,
please raise Longyue for me until she marries.
But...
but Longyue is your own daughter!
Why would you ...
Hongyan and Lingxi occupy all the time I have.
Longyue sees you as her mother.
If I force her to live with me,
that would truly break our bond as mother and daughter.
Hearing you say this,
I will love and care for Longyue with all my strength.
Your wholehearted devotion to Longyue
makes me incomparable to you despite being her birth mother.
By helping me raise Longyue,
you are helping me protect all three of my children.
Thank you.
By the grace of Heaven, His Majesty decrees:
“Consort Lumière of the Niohuru family demonstrates brilliant honor and virtue,
and upholds herself with great modesty and prudence.
At Her Majesty the Empress Dowager’s benevolent behest,
I hereby grant her the title of Noble Consort Lumière.”
This is His Majesty’s decree.
I thank Your Majesty for the heavenly grace.
This is the golden book and golden seal of the Noble Consort
for Your Noble Highness's reverent acceptance.
I thank His Majesty.
His Majesty the Emperor.
- Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
- Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
What brings Your Majesty here?
I couldn't wait to see you.
Instead of waiting at the Palace of Great Benevolence,
I would much rather accompany you there.
The more magnificent the ceremony,
the more the ceremonial procedures must be followed.
Please ride in the sedan chair. I shall follow Your Majesty.
Huan Huan, you always remember the
Han Dynasty etiquette of declining the sedan.
That which I cherish I will never forget.
You said the same thing to me when we were
leaving for the Hot Spring Palace.
Your Majesty still remembers?
I shall never forget.
Noble Consort Lumière of the Niohuru family.
By the grace of Heaven's decree to the palace,
may you cultivate virtue and bring peace to the imperial harem.
May you diligently serve His Majesty and
expand the imperial family.
I am delighted to obey Your Majesty's advice.
Noble Consort Lumière has a brilliant intellect
and a perceptive mind.
Since you have not been in very good health,
you should take some time to recuperate.
I plan to give Noble Consort Lumière the authority
to assist in palace management.
She will take care of all the trivial matters in the palace.
What are your thoughts on this?
It is certainly a good thing.
But although I have not been feeling well,
Noble Consort Lumière has to take care of her newborns
and soon Princess Longyue will return
to the Palace of Eternal Longevity.
I'm concerned that Noble Consort Lumière
won't have time to manage everything,
with such additional burden on her responsibilities.
I've already discussed this with Noble Consort Lumière.
We have agreed it would be best for Consort Estime
to continue raising Longyue.
There is no need to move her away.
As for Hongyan and Lingxi, their nursemaids take care of them.
Noble Consort Lumière won't have much to attend to.
It seems like my concerns were unnecessary.
But this is the first time that Noble Consort Lumière
would be managing palace affairs.
These matters may seem trivial but are numerous.
To help ease the burden, how about...
Your Majesty is right.
Compared to the concubines senior to me,
I am young and inexperienced.
Consort Honnête entered the family the earliest,
and Consort Estime assisted Your Majesty
with palace affairs for many years.
I am more than willing to ask them for advice.
It's wonderful that you feel that way.
Do you have any more advice for
Noble Consort Lumière?
Noble Consort Lumière,
now that you are the head of concubines,
you must be diligent in managing the palace affairs
as well as serving His Majesty to
add a few more heirs to the imperial family.
Your Majesty has personally educated me.
I will not disappoint Your Majesty's expectations.
Your knees will hurt from kneeling for too long.
You may rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Make good use of your golden seal.
It's no longer just a cold block of gold.
Your Majesty, I'm going to get changed.
May I ask Your Majesty and Noble Consort Lumière
to go ahead to the Palace of Layered Brilliance
to accept the ceremonial respects from the concubines?
"A man's passion is strong as warm liquor;
a woman's affection is soft as tender silk."
"The heated liquor can grow cold,
but the tender silk is never severed."
My wish is that Your Majesty will treat
Noble Consort Lumière like that unsevered silk.
Please drink up, Your Majesty.
Well said!
Congratulations to Noble Consort Lumière.
All may be seated.
I'll join you in your palace tonight.
Today is the one-month anniversary
of Hongyan and Lingxi's birth.
I am afraid their older sister Longyue will be jealous.
Why doesn't Your Majesty spend some time with Longyue
in Consort Estime's palace on my behalf?
Longyue will definitely feel happy.
Just as well.
I can't let Longyue feel like I'm neglecting her
now that she has a little brother and sister.
My Lady, this is for you to nourish your hands.
It is top-quality rose water.
Your hands will become fragrant and soft.
Where are Hongyan and Lingxi?
The nursemaids are nursing them.
Your Highness, there are so many congratulatory gifts.
I need more time to sort through all of them.
You have good taste.
Only tell me about those that capture your eyes.
This is from State Prince Jinkang.
It is a set of a dozen fans made of
gold-painted silk voile, antler, and bamboo.
The most marvelous thing is that the bamboo feels so cool on your hands,
just like jade.
And there's this.
The Duke of Pei gifted poison-detecting chopsticks
made of grooved rhinoceros horn.
Although silver chopsticks can also detect poison,
they are far less precious than these.
People who use poison are the most insidious.
You can never be too vigilant.
The Duke of Pei is thoughtful to offer these.
Is it the Duke of Pei from the Meng family?
Yes.
His daughter, Meng Jingxian,
was to be betrothed to Lord XVII.
I wonder if she is married already.
Not yet.
Miss Meng admires Lord XVII wholeheartedly.
She still "hasn't stepped out of her maiden's chamber."
Now she is an old maid.
Does she think she can marry Lord XVII
by waiting until she's old?
His Lordship has so many admirers.
I bet His Lordship has never even looked at her brows and eyes.
Why are you so angry?
Your remarks are so callous.
I just can't stand the way she is.
She's scared there might be people who
don't know she is waiting for him.
It embarrasses His Lordship.
The gifts are all about the same.
Put away the common ones
so we can reward them to others.
The other gifts are not worth mentioning.
In my eyes, this coral bracelet from
Noble Prince Guo is most exquisite.
"Coral is not to be cherished in the palm of your hand;
It is to be enshrined as a flower in the Shangyang Palace."
My Lady.
His Majesty will stay with Consort Estime tonight.
Meizhuang is not feeling well.
We shall go visit her.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Follow us to get updates on the translation progress.
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Peace to Noble Consort Lumière.
Stop the litter.
Peace to you as well, Noble Lady Paix.
I see you are out enjoying the pleasant night.
I'm just taking a short walk.
I shall return shortly to cuddle with Velvet Ball and sleep.
Velvet Ball is such an adorable cat.
I'm wondering if she's grown larger.
If Your Highness is interested,
why not stop by my Hall of Spring Joy?
I wonder if Your Highness will deign to grace my humble abode?
However, Your Highness is attended by so many servants;
I'm afraid they will frighten my Velvet Ball into silence.
As Your Highness knows
the best thing about Velvet Ball is her meow.
Under this intoxicating moonlight,
it would be a shame if I do not join you.
Jade, help me up.
It is quite rare to receive your invitation.
I shall pay a visit to your residence.
You all don't need to follow us.
What do you want?
Do not underestimate this dagger, Your Highness.
I was attacked by a reckless leopard once.
I then sneaked into its cave,
and slit its throat.
If Jade finds herself screaming,
then this very dagger
may find itself slitting Consort Lumière's throat.
There is no need to terrify Jade.
You lured me here
and allowed Jade to accompany us.
You must have a thorough plan.
Brilliant, Your Highness.
If I lose all constraint and kill Your Highness and your servant,
the Pavilion of Twining Reeds is right up ahead -
I can easily turn Lady Délice into my scapegoat.
After all, it's not just recently
she developed the desire to kill Your Highness.
I might as well grant her this wish.
Don't you also harbor hatred against me?
Otherwise, why would you allow Velvet Ball
to attract so many cats,
trying to take my life and the lives of my children?
Your Highness was aware of that,
yet you tolerated me for so long.
I didn't want to give you trouble over your devoted love.
But now you are a favored concubine of His Majesty.
It's not worthwhile to kill me
for the sake of Noble Prince Guo.
So you knew.
You love the "coupling joy" flowers more than your own life.
Someone also told me that
Noble Prince Guo sent an imperial doctor to save you
when you were alone and on the brink of death years ago.
I wonder what he will think if he finds out he saved a woman
"as vicious as the snakes and scorpions".
His Lordship made a great effort to save your life,
but you are so vile!
Are you even worthy to admire His Lordship?
You weren't angry when your mistress said I harmed her,
why become agitated when His Lordship is mentioned?
You!
You demoness!
If I am a demoness,
does that not make Noble Consort Lumière
the head of all demons?
Your fate led you to be with him -
but you were insatiable.
You bewitched the Emperor and returned.
In Your Highness's heart,
does the imperial status and opulence really surpass
His Lordship's love and devotion?
Ever since I met His Lordship,
I've only known that he's the most
gallant and free-spirited man under Heaven.
I've never seen him so frustrated, dispirited, and haggard.
My suspicions were aroused
the moment Your Highness returned to the Palace.
And at the Mid-Autumn Festival banquet...
You were the one eavesdropping that night.
And what of it?
Do you think I am unworthy to admire His Lordship?
But you, Noble Consort Lumière, are even less worthy of him!
If I kill you,
it will just remove one more heartless woman from this world.
You will also be taking His Lordship's life
if anything happens to My Lady.
All these years, only His Lordship has treated me well.
Therefore, anyone who hurts him deserves to die.
If you don't spare me, you will harm him as well.
It's not that I don't want to spare you.
It's just that there is no place
for unfaithful people under Heaven.
How would you know...
Sometimes, unfaithfulness is its own punishment.
Where...? Where did you get this?
This coral bracelet is from the South Sea;
it was His Lordship's prized possession.
He has never shown it to anyone.
Why do you have this?
You should ask the owner of this bracelet.
Your Lordship...
You owe her nothing.
Why are you unable to move on?
Forget it.
His Lordship gave you his heart.
If you have any sense of conscience at all
you should condemn yourself every day.
The kind treatment I received from His Lordship
might be absolutely nothing in your eyes.
However, to me ...
it is warmth I will never again embrace in my life.
I'm letting you go today
to repay His Lordship's kindness to me.
What a lunatic!
No harm was done.
Lady Paix went to extremes for her passion and emotions.
Noble Consort Lumière has great good fortune indeed.
The "dragon and phoenix twins" have secured
her a lifetime of honor and riches.
Just giving birth is nothing to be proud of.
We'll see if she is capable of bringing them up.
Easy for you to say that, Délice.
Certainly.
An, you are of ill omen.
Even Concubine Vertu avoids you while she's pregnant.
If you walk around Noble Consort Lumière's palace more often,
I wonder if her children can stay alive.
Silence, both of you!
Both of you are so good with words
but cannot talk yourselves into His Majesty's favor.
Noble Lady Délice, since you were released from confinement
you haven't been able to restore
His Majesty's favor for you.
Concubine An, you've been trapped by
this astrological situation for so long
and have shown no ability to save yourself.
Neither of you can make yourself helpful to me.
All you do is bicker.
What's the use of you two?
Use your wits well.
Otherwise, this whole harem will be taken by Zhen Huan!
That bitch! She dared compete with me!
Concubine An, you come from such lowly beginnings
yet you've been on equal footing with me for so long.
I've tolerated you enough.
My Lady, your sleep tonic is ready.
Drink it before you retire to bed.
Coua...
Coua!
My voice!
What happened to my voice?
My Lady, what happened to you?
My voice... without it I will never gain favor again.
Coua.
My Lady, someone did this to you.
I'm going to inform Her Majesty.
I'm going to beg her to help us.
Don't go!
My voice is all I have to gain His Majesty's favor.
If anyone finds out what happened to my voice,
His Majesty will surely no longer care for me.
Then I will become a useless pawn.
A discarded pawn!
Coua, remember this: I only caught a cold.
I will recover shortly.
I understand, My Lady.
Your Highness, look!
- Elder sister!
- Yurao!
- My Second Lady!
- Peace to Your Noble Highness.
Yurao, let me get a good look at you.
It is a joyous occasion to finally reunite
after so many years,
so why are you crying, elder sister?
Sister Jade.
My Second Lady has grown a lot taller.
His Majesty is so happy for Your Highness
that he especially invited Your Highness's family to the palace.
His Majesty also said
your sister should feel comfortable staying in the palace
to keep Your Highness company.
Where are my parents?
Are they here as well?
Mr. Zhen is still recuperating in the capital.
His Majesty has also summoned your mother
and sister back to Beijing.
Your sister traveled day and night
to put Your Highness at peace.
I believe both Mr. and Lady Zhen
will be able to see each other in a few days.
I appreciate His Majesty's kind intentions.
However, my father is still a guilty official.
Although His Majesty granted them the grace
to be summoned back to the capital,
what does this achieve
besides adding to their fatigue?
Although His Majesty did not restore Mr. Zhen's old position,
he has ordered your family's former residence to be renovated
so your parents can reside in the capital
and happily enjoy their years ahead.
I understand.
I will thank His Majesty for his grace tomorrow.
You may take your leave now.
Yes. There's one more matter.
Lord XVII said
that in congratulations of Your Highness's promotion,
he grants Your Highness all of the "coupling joy" trees
in the Hall of Converging Light
in addition to the other gifts.
His Lordship said,
the "coupling joy" flower is excellent at soothing
the five organs and the mind.
Your Highness may enjoy the beauty of the flowers
or cook them with porridge.
He hopes you won't let them go to waste.
I acknowledge His Lordship's thoughtfulness.
Please convey my thanks to His Lordship.
This Lord XVII has a uniquely thoughtful mind.
He is unlike others,
who only present gold or jade.
This is your first day in the palace, My Second Lady.
You probably have no idea
how unconventional Lord XVII is.
Before Your Highness returned,
I had already ordered some servants to clear out
the Hall of Eternal Treasure
where My Second Lady will reside.
Wonderful.
We need not stand out here any longer.
Let's all go inside.
I shall take my leave.
Your Majesty was reading memorandums all night.
It is much too tiring.
Noble Consort Lumière is busy
taking care of two children.
It is inconvenient for her to serve Your Majesty.
There are many brilliant and youthful concubines in the harem.
Perhaps Your Majesty can pay them more visits as well.
I heard Concubine An got sick from something she ate.
Her voice has been ruined.
I'm afraid she is not capable of singing anymore.
What a shame.
At first, it was just a cold.
She could have recovered in a few days.
Who would've thought that her medicine
could hurt her throat even more.
I fear she might not even be able
to talk properly in the future.
Well then, let her take time to recuperate.
I haven't visited Concubine Vertu in a while.
Huan Huan has already given birth.
We're all waiting for Meizhuang's good news.
Lumière.
Who is it?
- Lumière.
- Lower the sedan.
Lower the sedan chair.
Peace to Noble Consort Lumiere.
After just a few months, have you forgotten me, Lumiere?
Not that I forgot you.
It's just that seeing you so weak and feeble....
Your disappointment must be colder than this bitter weather.
I've seen how people change like the weather
and grown used to them belittling me.
I'm not afraid of being disappointed.
His Majesty ordered you to recuperate alone
and avoid seeing people.
Why today, did you decide to come out?
Others avoid me fearing my ill omen.
You know best whether I carry bad fortune
and what my misfortune truly is.
I meant only to express concern for your well-being.
Why do you say you're bad luck?
It saddens me to hear
such self-contempt and self-degradation.
Your circumstance is already inconvenient.
Why insist on coming out to speak of such burdensome thoughts?
Perhaps your current predicament
was caused by over-exerting your mind.
You know that I come from lowly origins.
There are so many noble people in this world,
making me all the more insignificant.
I can only strive to become stronger.
It is definitely good to stengthen oneself.
Just not in an immoral way that costs innocent lives.
If one plots every step of the way and becomes insatiable,
excessive self-strengthening will become self-harm.
Now no one is stronger than you in the palace,
whereas no one is more abject and abandoned than me.
You are the most blessed person, Lumière.
I can turn peril into safety
if I can dip myself in your good fortune.
With you as my sister, what would I fear?
I wish your auspicious words would come true.
I certainly remember how, as my sister,
you treated me with such deep affection.
I will "repay every drop of 'kindness' with a fountain of gratitude."
You can count on me for this.
I also feel the same way.
Judging from her voice, her throat is truly ruined.
I don't know if it was ordained by Heaven or arranged by man.
My Lady, now that she's lost favor,
it's a good chance for us to send her off quietly.
In the palace, death is the best way out.
She enjoyed His Majesty's favor for many years
and has a strong character.
Now that she lost favor and is humiliated,
life is a hundred times more agonizing
than death for her.
I understand.
I will inform the other concubines to take good care of Concubine An.
What are you doing? What are you doing?
Damaging the room of Her Highness?
Stop putting up talismans! Stop!
Concubine An, we are doing this for your own good.
Even His Majesty said you're bad luck.
We made a special trip to the Baohua Hall
to get talisman papers and water to drive out evil spirits.
Put up more talismans.
Don't forget the quilt and cabinet.
What on earth are you doing?
Don't spray the water!
Are you all out of your mind?
Even if Her Highness is inauspicious,
it is not your place to disturb
the Palace of Prolonging Happiness.
Concubine An bears ill fortune which harms the harem.
Therefore it concerns everyone.
The talismans won't be effective if they are not burned.
Burn them quickly.
My Lady, as expected, Concubine Fidèle
and Attendant Kang
went to the Palace of Prolonging Happiness
and created a disturbance.
Does the Empress know about this?
She probably does.
But she didn't inquire about it any further.
Just let them be. There's more to come.
My Lady, the charcoal has run out.
Please use this hot water bottle to warm yourself.
We only have a little hot water remaining
and we also need to drink and wash our faces.
How can we afford to use it in hot water bottles?
It snowed several times and is getting colder and colder.
I have covered you with all the quilts we have.
We would freeze to death if it were not for
the underground heating.
Would anybody know if we freeze to death here?
My Lady.
How has Your Highness been doing?
Concubine Fidèle and I have been thinking of you.
What are you up to this time?
We brought some charcoal for you
since we are all sisters
and we know you don't have enough.
Bring it in.
Light it.
How can you survive the cold and the snow without charcoal?
But Concubine An, you need to understand that
times have changed.
We can't afford to give you any high-quality charcoal.
You'll have to make do with this.
Stop! Stop! The smoke is suffocating.
Quick, get the fire going!
Otherwise how can you get warm?
As the head of the Palace of Prolonging Happiness,
I order you to leave
and stop your misbehavior here!
Do you still think you're the favored Concubine An?
Forget about that.
Your life now is worse than my servants.
"Don't wave a chicken feather like a commander's arrow!"
Stop making noise!
The Empress Dowager is sick and needs rest.
Who dares to make a scene here?
Her Majesty the Empress is aware of what has happened here,
so she ordered me to deliver her decree.
The servants of the Palace of Prolonging Happiness
were unable to protect their mistress.
They will forfeit one month's stipend.
The servants of Concubine Fidèle and Attendant Kang
failed to persuade their mistresses not to make trouble.
- They are penalized with a fine of three months' stipend.
- Yes.
Take this away quickly.
My Lady, please be assured.
Although Her Majesty is also in a difficult situation,
she has never forgotten about you.
She bade me bring you quilts and charcoal
so you won't have these worries over the winter.
I thank Her Majesty for her benevolence.
Sparrow, take them.
Yes.
Ever since your throat became damaged,
His Majesty has not mentioned you.
My Lady, you need to find a new path forward.
Your Majesty.
Is it done?
Yes.
"Adding flowers to the brocade" never earns you true gratitude.
"Sending charcoal on a snowy day"
makes people remember your kindness.
I've told her all that should be said.
Hopefully she will learn from it.
Only when one is in a desperate situation
do they learn to fight back and press ahead without hesitating.
I'm helping her by asking you to advise her.
Since Noble Lady Délice has already made this move,
Concubine An's throat is unlikely to recover.
I might as well ruin it once and for all.
Even the parrot of Noble Lady Paix can recite poems now.
Concubine An should think of a new strategy.
Your Majesty is wise.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.